<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>swhite (Stephen)</title>
    <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/swhite-stephen/1290</link>
    <description>Steven White.  I have been a programmer since 1974, working for local governments.  Some would say I have 43 years of experience, others would say I have one year of experience repeated 43 times.  I started trying to learn REBOL when &quot;REBOL The Official Guide&quot; came out, but couldn&#39;t quite &quot;get&quot; it.  And then I finally did.  Now I use R2 a lot for little data manipulation programs at work, quite a few it turns out when I count them.  Lately, as I write something that seems like it might be useful to others, I generalize it and sanitize it and put it on a little web site I made at www.cobolrebol.com.  I still feel like a REBOL beginner.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2018 03:06:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Introductions</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/swhite-stephen/1290.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>swhite (Stephen)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[swhite]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Steven White.  I have been a programmer since 1974, working for local governments.  Some would say I have 43 years of experience, others would say I have one year of experience repeated 43 times.  I started trying to learn REBOL when "REBOL The Official Guide" came out, but couldn't quite "get" it.  And then I finally did.  Now I use R2 a lot for little data manipulation programs at work, quite a few it turns out when I count them.  Lately, as I write something that seems like it might be useful to others, I generalize it and sanitize it and put it on a little web site I made at <a href="http://www.cobolrebol.com" rel="nofollow noopener">www.cobolrebol.com</a>.  I still feel like a REBOL beginner.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/swhite-stephen/1290/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/swhite-stephen/1290/1</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2018 03:06:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-post-1290-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/swhite-stephen/1290.rss">swhite (Stephen)</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
