<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Introductions - AltRebol</title>
    <link>https://forum.rebol.info/c/introductions/46</link>
    <description>Topics in the &#39;Introductions&#39; category If you&#39;re using a pseudonym here, then we&#39;d appreciate it if you would post a little about your experience with Rebol (or what got you interested).</description>
    
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 02:35:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <atom:link href="https://forum.rebol.info/c/introductions/46.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <item>
          <title>Cggong</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[cggong]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I'm building a C GUI application with GTK and Ren-C, a client for some social media websites, which would support filtering of posts based on keywords and rules.<br>
I explored various ways of doing networking. R3 networking seems more complex than R2. While the additions in R3 and Ren-C should helpful for many use cases, currently my use case only needs the ability to download a web page.<br>
I'm planning to use libcurl for now. To put things in perspective a little bit, in order to read a URL in libcurl, it would take a callback function with <a href="https://curl.se/libcurl/c/CURLOPT_WRITEFUNCTION.html" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">CURLOPT_WRITEFUNCTION</a>. Whenever new data arrives from the network, the callback function would be called, similar to the behavior of read mentioned in the top post.<br>
Using Rebol doesn't seem to reduce much complexity here, so I wouldn't mind using C for now...</p>
            <p><small>18 posts - 4 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/cggong/1776">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/cggong/1776</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 02:35:32 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1776</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/cggong/1776.rss">Cggong</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Ingo (Ingo Hohmann)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[IngoHohmann]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>As I have kinda been asked to introduce myself as well, here goes.</p>
<p>I found Rebol at the beginning of the 2.0 Cycle. First because of the 40+ Systems, then because of the easy way to create 80s Cash Register GUIs. Then I really got to like parse.</p>
<p>I knew to program a little more than "Hello World" in COBOL, Prolog, Pascal, Modula-2, Oberon, Lisp, Smalltalk, C, Java, Javascript, Powershell and Rebol. Though today, I guess I would have to look up hello world for some of these <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/wink.png?v=9" title=":wink:" class="emoji" alt=":wink:"> .</p>
<p>At work I work with Powershell, personally I would go for Rebol, some Lisp or Smalltalk.</p>
<p>I programmed a few scripts for myself in Rebol, and put some on <a href="http://Rebol.org">Rebol.org</a>, but I guess most of these wouldn't work on todays Rebol Variants.</p>
<p>I am really fascinated by the direction(s) Brian bends the language, and by the pace this happens in.</p>
<p>I have no personal projects involving programming at the moment.</p>
<p>Kind regards,<br>
Ingo</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/ingo-ingo-hohmann/1612">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/ingo-ingo-hohmann/1612</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 16:46:09 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1612</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/ingo-ingo-hohmann/1612.rss">Ingo (Ingo Hohmann)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Giuseppe Chillemi</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[GiuseppeChillemi]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi,<br>
my name is Giuseppe, I work in a food production company and the order taking industry. I am developing different solutions for those markets and I am the sponsor of some bounties for Red, most notably a GRID component. I am an old Rebol lover, someone who has not understood more than the basic Rebol operations until 3 years ago. Now I master it but I am facing some limitations. I am on the Red world but some suggestions I have made have not been accepted. Red is more Rebol2+ with conservative ambient. As here I see some Rebels, let's see if there is space for my unconventional ideas. In case they will be accepted and implemented, I will work continue on Rebol3 by HF for some of my projects!</p>
<p>Giuseppe Chillemi</p>
            <p><small>4 posts - 3 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/giuseppe-chillemi/1507">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/giuseppe-chillemi/1507</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2021 16:38:45 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1507</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/giuseppe-chillemi/1507.rss">Giuseppe Chillemi</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Danny, dRebol, Inetw3 (Daniel Murrill)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[Danny]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hello Hostilefork,</p>
<p>I've been following Rebol since 1993-94, over 20 years, as dRebol,Inetw3, and I am still amazed. I may not be a good programmer but I do dream in Rebol.</p>
<p>I posted the <a href="http://www.rebol.org/view-script.r?script=rebol-dom.r" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">%Rebol-dom.r script</a> to rebol-org and it has some vague similarities to your TLS EMIT dialect. Especially the VAR LET variables that bind to functions. I've saw discussions on SO about it.  I check it 2-3 times every day.</p>
<p>I thought I was crazy using a var function to turn set-word!s into a named variable functions bound to data. I don't know how to optimize the code but it must look like, say, javascript or lua as much as possible for my next two DSL's.</p>
<p>I think you given me hope to keep trying. Every new chosen path starts with a Pandora's Box.</p>
            <p><small>2 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/danny-drebol-inetw3-daniel-murrill/1502">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/danny-drebol-inetw3-daniel-murrill/1502</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 21:41:53 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1502</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/danny-drebol-inetw3-daniel-murrill/1502.rss">Danny, dRebol, Inetw3 (Daniel Murrill)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>introducing okram (Marko)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[okram]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi, I've been programming since the mid-70s, first in FORTRAN IV and the proprietary language of the Olivetti P652. Various BASICs around 1980. Then lots of C. Switched to Haskell as my primary language in 1992 (but don't really like the complexity it has acquired over time). For the little programming I do nowadays I use C++ when speed is an issue and I'm looking for a language for those occasions when it isn't as much an issue. That's how I encountered Rebol/RenC/Red a few weeks ago.</p>
            <p><small>5 posts - 3 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/introducing-okram-marko/1447">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/introducing-okram-marko/1447</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 16:56:01 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1447</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/introducing-okram-marko/1447.rss">introducing okram (Marko)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Razetime (Raghu)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[razetime]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hey there. I'm Raghu.</p>
<p>I've been coding since I was 10, mostly for the fun of it, and I still am. I'm currently studying Computer Science at SRMIST.</p>
<p>I program mostly in Ruby, and I make HTML5 games as well.</p>
<p>I found Rebol through hostilefork's RebMu and Codegolf(which I am hopelessly addicted to right now). Nice to meet you all.</p>
            <p><small>2 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/razetime-raghu/1400">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/razetime-raghu/1400</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 02:09:05 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1400</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/razetime-raghu/1400.rss">Razetime (Raghu)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Pierre (Pierre Chevalier)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[Pierre]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I am a French geologist, currently taking a 180 degree sharp curve in my professional life.<br>
After ca. 30 years of practicing geology and mining exploration worldwide, I just went back to university in Bordeaux, to study computer science (<a href="https://dept-info.labri.fr/adsillh/">https://dept-info.labri.fr/adsillh/</a> is the cursus I'm attending).</p>
<p>I've been coding with *Basic languages since 1983, with C (occasionally) since 1990, and I saw the Light when I started coding in Rebol 2 around 2001 or 2002.  I've been working with plenty of other languages, not worth mentioning.</p>
<p>GNU/Linux user since 1999, exclusive GNU/Linux user since 2005, currently Debian and Devuan are giving life to most of my computers.</p>
<p>My Rebol experience has always been interrupted: I started with great enthusiasm and productivity; then in 2007 I wanted to subcontract the development of a tool for geologists and I wished it would be developed in Rebol: but the subcontractor didn't want, because Rebol wasn't open source software... so they (and I) switched to python for a while.  Then on 12/12/12, full of Hope, I started Rebolling again intensively, putting much hope on the Red adventure.  Today, whenever I have some quick code to do, Rebol2 comes as THE solution.</p>
<p>Most of what I (quite messily) coded is on my github:<br>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://github.githubassets.com/favicons/favicon.svg" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">
      <a href="https://github.com/pierrechtux/geolllibre" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <img src="https://avatars3.githubusercontent.com/u/3036630?s=400&amp;v=4" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar" width="77" height="77">

<h3><a href="https://github.com/pierrechtux/geolllibre" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pierrechtux/geolllibre</a></h3>

<p>Free Libre Open Source Software for Geology - Géologie Logiciels Libres - pierrechtux/geolllibre</p>


  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
</p>
<p>I feel like a perpetual Rebol beginner...</p>
            <p><small>5 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/pierre-pierre-chevalier/1339">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/pierre-pierre-chevalier/1339</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 17:46:34 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1339</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/pierre-pierre-chevalier/1339.rss">Pierre (Pierre Chevalier)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>About the Introductions category</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[gchiu]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>If you're using a pseudonym here, then we'd appreciate it if you would post a little about your experience with Rebol (or what got you interested).</p>
<p>And of course, if you're a long time Rebol user back from whenever, and have been on the mailing list etc, then feel free to mention this.  Add any Github or other Repos, and LinkedIn if you wish.</p>
<p>Please post your introduction as a <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/c/introductions">New Topic in the Introductions Category</a>, vs. a reply to this message.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/about-the-introductions-category/1286">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/about-the-introductions-category/1286</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>Yes</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>Yes</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1286</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/about-the-introductions-category/1286.rss">About the Introductions category</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>salotz (Samuel)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[salotz]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I am a PhD student in Biochemistry at Michigan State for the time being, but basically my role is data scientist and software engineer. I am primarily in python because it is easy to get started and the data science libraries and support and adoption in academia/research is huge.</p>
<p>Interested in rebol for a variety of reasons, but primarily interested in solving problems related to what I like to call "exploratory" programming. Structured software engineering is a well covered topic but doesn't really help with what a data scientist does on a daily basis which is trying new things and iteratively building those into a real processing pipeline which may not have a very long lifetime but can still be overburdened with complexity. The intuition for what I mean is anything that you would either write a slew of unportable bash scripts with really long and overly specific names or maybe Jupyter notebooks or Mathematica. In my experience "scripting" (i.e. the UNIX tradition of bash, sed, awk, perl and other treacherous demons) OS facilities like filesystems and process management is the weakest link in the data scientist's toolbox, which has led to solutions like Jupyter and DataBricks. Which are unusable in a number of other ways. The block orientation of rebol IMO is the proper foundation for making this kind of work tractable and maybe even comfortable. My long term goal would be to use rebol as a document container format (replaces e.g. a "notebook" or filesystem "schema") that also allows for creation and orchestration of pipelines of blocks. Sort of like "literate programming" but the literate part is also programmable.</p>
<p>I am going to do a write up with real examples of where I think rebol could help; drawing from my personal emacs org-mode notebooks and project folders I use for doing my PhD work.  Let me know if you are interested and it might come sooner.</p>
<p>Currently other interests include sane system configuration management (Nix, Guix, Genode), object capabilities systems for collaborative programming (Genode and Monte), language-oriented programming (rebol and racket), programming/operating assistants as I like to call them (e.g. emacs, DrRacket, Dark language, McCLIM), solid-state computers (e.g. Urbit and Smalltalk) and probabilistic programming. I'm also pretty interested in using Nim, if I can get over not having the python libraries, ReasonML, and Clojure for doing "real work".</p>
            <p><small>4 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/salotz-samuel/1287">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/salotz-samuel/1287</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 17:31:41 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1287</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/salotz-samuel/1287.rss">salotz (Samuel)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>George-Zipperlen</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[George-Zipperlen]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>George Zipperlen, speaking at you:</p>
<p>New to Rebol, thanks to <a class="mention" href="/u/hostilefork">@hostilefork</a> presentation at Philly Lambda functional programming meetup, and invite to Rebol [2019] conference.</p>
<p>Started out in pure math, first language APL -- Just get things done !<br>
Rude awakening to FORTRAN</p>
<p>Ruder awakening to PL/I  and JCL</p>
<p>Systems programming in Pascal, and assembler because Pascal forbids you to...</p>
<p>C / Unix / shell, sed, awk, perl, TCL -- more getting things done and shooting myself in foot.</p>
<p>SQL, MatLab, S/R  -- powerful, but slow and clunky</p>
<p>CommonLisp for natural language processing -- Ugh!</p>
<p>Smalltalk for digital telephony -- loved it</p>
<p>C++ and Java -- rude awakening from the pleasures of object oriented programming to obsessive inheritance hierarchies.  Revenge of the Pascal nanny</p>
<p>Python, somewhat elegant.  Machines now fast enough that it's usable...</p>
            <p><small>3 posts - 3 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/george-zipperlen/1288">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/george-zipperlen/1288</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2019 00:14:50 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1288</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/george-zipperlen/1288.rss">George-Zipperlen</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>LkpPo (Stéphane)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[LkpPo]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>(HostilFork asks me to introduce myself.)</p>
<p>Stéphane Aulery. French Rebol beginner. I have an IT BTS (a non-university French degree in development). I have been working for 13 years in web development and the development of other business applications. Almost never at a software publisher. For 16 years I use Linux, especially Debian, but also Windows. Since then I want to switch to OpenBSD because of my affinity with this project and its developers.</p>
<p>I am passionate about computer science and programming and I spend a lot of time both contributing to free software and learning all kinds of languages ​​and paradigms.</p>
<p>I had the opportunity to develop the entire system of a publisher in ASP / VBScript, then work on the systems of other companies, which made me refractory to complexity. You could tell me that ASP / VbScript is not very engaging, but this minimalist language, in Oberon / Modula / Pascal's mind, really captures the essence of structured programming in a way that makes me see Perl, PHP, Python, Ruby like monsters. On the other hand I do not have much experience with compiled languages ​​because it is not common in my professional sector (just some experiments on microcontrollers or C drivers during my studies).</p>
<p>I do not remember when I met Rebol. Perhaps during research on Forth and Lisp. I decided to take a more serious interest in Rebol. I am here for pleasure, curiosity, learning, and contributing a promising language.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/lkppo-stephane/1289">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/lkppo-stephane/1289</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 23:06:35 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1289</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/lkppo-stephane/1289.rss">LkpPo (Stéphane)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>swhite (Stephen)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[swhite]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Steven White.  I have been a programmer since 1974, working for local governments.  Some would say I have 43 years of experience, others would say I have one year of experience repeated 43 times.  I started trying to learn REBOL when "REBOL The Official Guide" came out, but couldn't quite "get" it.  And then I finally did.  Now I use R2 a lot for little data manipulation programs at work, quite a few it turns out when I count them.  Lately, as I write something that seems like it might be useful to others, I generalize it and sanitize it and put it on a little web site I made at <a href="http://www.cobolrebol.com" rel="nofollow noopener">www.cobolrebol.com</a>.  I still feel like a REBOL beginner.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/swhite-stephen/1290">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/swhite-stephen/1290</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2018 03:06:38 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1290</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/swhite-stephen/1290.rss">swhite (Stephen)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>BlackATTR (Ed O&#39;Connor)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[BlackATTR]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Ed O'Connor. Liberal arts major, Brown U, 1991. Never took a CS course, I'm a self-taught scripter. I don't know how to build Ren-C or Red or use Github. I found Rebol pretty early, around '97-- I'm still a believer in end-user/personal programming. I'd like to see redbol make a name for itself in dialecting, DSLs &amp; mini-languages. I have dialect ideas for workflows, scheduling &amp; crontabs, taxonomy management, marketing automation and others.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ed-o-connor-9654a/" rel="nofollow noopener">LinkedIn</a></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/blackattr-ed-oconnor/1291">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/blackattr-ed-oconnor/1291</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2017 23:48:58 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1291</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/blackattr-ed-oconnor/1291.rss">BlackATTR (Ed O&#39;Connor)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>draegtun (Barry)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[draegtun]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Barry Walsh, Freelance IT Consultant from London, UK.  Stalwart from Market Research industry! Escaped briefly into Management Consultancy and then a failed web CRM start-up before going solo with <a href="http://www.draegtun.com" rel="nofollow noopener">Draegtun Systems Ltd</a></p>
<p>Self taught programmer using mixture of proprietary languages until I discovered Perl in 1995.  This was my first introduction to an opensource <a href="https://metacpan.org/author/DRAEGTUN" rel="nofollow noopener">community</a>.  With Perl I developed a websurvey system used on one of the largest continual surveys.</p>
<p>First came across Rebol when it was opensourced on 12-12-2012 via a HN article.  I think dialects and parse is what attracted me most to the language.</p>
<p>Most development I do now uses Rebol 3.   And I've used Cheyenne on last few web projects.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/draegtun" rel="nofollow noopener">Github</a> | <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/draegtun/" rel="nofollow noopener">LinkedIn</a></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/draegtun-barry/1292">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/draegtun-barry/1292</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2017 14:49:32 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1292</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/draegtun-barry/1292.rss">draegtun (Barry)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>iArnold (Arnold)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[iArnold]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Arnold van Hofwegen, studied Math at RUG, Netherlands.<br>
Found Rebol in 2011.<br>
Created a checkers program in Rebol that can beat me (probably not so hard), created a program to play Chinese Chess (Xiangqi) in Red.<br>
Spoiled forever, professionally bound to far less superior far more bloated mainstream technologies.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/iarnold-arnold/1297">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/iarnold-arnold/1297</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2017 11:41:17 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1297</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/iarnold-arnold/1297.rss">iArnold (Arnold)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Brett (Brett Handley)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[Brett]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Brett Handley, studied Math and Computing at Uni and got paid for applications development in Investment Management, Property, Accounting and Manufacturing job scheduling software.</p>
<p>Got interested in Rebol around 2000, now my brain is ruined because I think terms of Rebol and get caught up with obscure ideas such as parsing and Rebol expression evaluation.</p>
<p>Still hoping to use Rebol to create apps seamlessly on mobile and desktop.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/brett-brett-handley/1293">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/brett-brett-handley/1293</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 03:42:56 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1293</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/brett-brett-handley/1293.rss">Brett (Brett Handley)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>kealist (Joshua)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[kealist]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Joshua Shireman, Grinnell CS, Used Rebol since before it was released, but have been a much heavier user in various projects since 2004.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/kealist-joshua/1296">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/kealist-joshua/1296</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:23:01 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1296</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/kealist-joshua/1296.rss">kealist (Joshua)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>gchiu (Graham)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[gchiu]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Graham Chiu, MD equivalent in NZ, and a rebol user since forever.  Main Rebol2 project is <a href="http://www.synapse-ehr.com/community/" rel="nofollow noopener">Synapse EHR</a> a medical database system for managing patients.</p>
<p>I'd like to be able to modernise that with R3 and a GUI .. perhaps one day.</p>
<p>My GitHub <a href="https://github.com/gchiu" rel="nofollow noopener">repo</a></p>
            <p><small>2 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/gchiu-graham/1295">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/gchiu-graham/1295</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2017 22:27:52 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1295</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/gchiu-graham/1295.rss">gchiu (Graham)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>hostilefork (Brian)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Introductions</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Brian Dickens, Cornell EE, ex-Microsoft Research guy.  Went to film school in LA, learned more than I thought I would.</p>
<p>These days I seem like an old-school Rebol user.  But if you go back in the history, people who were around longer, thought of me as the new guy who didn't get it.</p>
<p><a href="http://hostilefork.com" rel="nofollow noopener">Projects page</a> and <a href="http://blog.hostilefork.com" rel="nofollow noopener">more than you'd ever really want to know, on a blog (that I don't update very often anymore)</a></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/hostilefork-brian/1294">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/hostilefork-brian/1294</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2017 22:06:44 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1294</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/hostilefork-brian/1294.rss">hostilefork (Brian)</source>
        </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
