<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Rebol Foundation</title>
    <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450</link>
    <description>We&#39;ve talked at length for years about a foundation or committee of engaged Rebol users to help manage the Rebol assets including Rebol.org, and any other domains that RT no longer wish to maintain.  I&#39;d like this to extend to managing or help fund the new assets such as Rebol.info and Forum.rebol.info.

Yes, we&#39;ll need a charter and members, so if anyone has experience in these matters, let&#39;s discuss this one last time and actually get something done!</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 20:01:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Community</category>
    <atom:link href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Rebol Foundation</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[gchiu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>23 posts were split to a new topic: <a href="/t/rebol-org-new-design/469">Rebol.org new design</a></p>
          <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/10">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/10</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 20:24:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-post-450-10</guid>
        <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450.rss">Rebol Foundation</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rebol Foundation</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[gchiu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>We tend to use Ren-C instead of Ren/c because of those issues.</p>
<p>We already have the wiki, and the scripts on Github.  But we don't have rights to Carl's documents so it's basically a black box rewrite if we don't wish to be accused of plaigirism.</p>
<p>There is the <a href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Rebol_Programming" rel="nofollow noopener">Rebol Wiki Book</a> which many of us contributed to, but I thought it was a bit disorganised lacking a chief editor.</p>
<p>Ren-C is the only branch of the open source Rebol3 so I think we should present it as this if we take over <a href="http://Rebol.org" rel="nofollow noopener">Rebol.org</a>.  One of the points of taking over <a href="http://rebol.org" rel="nofollow noopener">rebol.org</a> is to position all of the documentation in its correct historical perspective, and point to the current alternatives.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/9">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/9</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 20:25:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-post-450-9</guid>
        <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450.rss">Rebol Foundation</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rebol Foundation</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[BlackATTR]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I'm in favor of archiving whatever useful Rebol 2 information that is available-- especially if it's easy (and thankfully this type of text tmunging is a forte for rebol). On the other hand, that stuff is <em>quite</em> dated, and my (mostly minor) concern about keeping that stuff available is that it's no longer reliable information and could easily become a source of misinformation. When writing Redbol and documenting it's already a bit of a chore to specify which interpreter and language branch it's intended for, I can only imagine the confusion it presents for newbies.</p>
<p>If Ren-C is to be positioned as a fully <em>reformed</em> Rebol (as opposed to Red, which in my mind is more of an evolution of Rebol 2.x-- shiny, buffed and rechromed, but an evolution nonetheless), then we likely need to reboot its documentation. Ren-C breaks with its Rebol past quite a bit, and I'm in favor of rewriting the documents to coincide with a major release. I'm also in favor of rewriting &amp; reformatting docs to highlight Ren-C's key differentiators-- 1, the new standards for writing clean/concise code in Ren-C (i.e., just lang basics here), 2, Ren-C for data wrangling in a networked world, and 3, advanced parse and dialecting (binding will have to get covered in there too).  I've been using <a href="https://twitter.github.io/typeahead.js/" rel="nofollow noopener">https://twitter.github.io/typeahead.js/</a> for large static documentation sites at work, so I think it might be a good to connect a lot of the available docs with these menus (another thought: a Ren-C adaptation of DITA XML would form a good document/content management resuse framework <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darwin_Information_Typing_Architecture" rel="nofollow noopener">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darwin_Information_Typing_Architecture</a>)</p>
<p>What do you think? I support archiving the older material and examining it as a reference/starting point for writing Ren-C's documentation but I also think we need to clean much of the outdated or conflicting information out there. It just muddies the water for anyone trying to get started with Ren-C (or Red, for that matter). Also, what are your thoughts about creating a public-facing site for Ren-C, to showcase all of these materials?  (Note: I see the name typed as Ren/C, which is may already be creating SEO issues.) Is now the right time to plan a new site for Ren-C, or are you thinking that github and other wikis are sufficient and this effort is mainly about consolidating/archiving the older Rebol materials?</p>
<p>(Edited for grammer &amp; clarity)</p>
          <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/8">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/8</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 00:31:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-post-450-8</guid>
        <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450.rss">Rebol Foundation</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rebol Foundation</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[rgchris]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I do have plans for backing up the script library—just need the will and cooperation to realise that*. The only important area of <a href="http://rebol.org" rel="nofollow noopener">rebol.org</a> I don't have contingency for is the Mailing List archive.</p>
<p>My thoughts are to break up areas of concern into separate subdomains and have a unifying homepage (for which the rebol.info homepage is my concept for how that might work and I believe the rebol.info domain sort of represents just now).</p>
<p>(*) though the notion of a script library seems a bit antiquated in the age of GitHub. I do wonder what role that might play now.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/7">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/7</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 23:10:51 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-post-450-7</guid>
        <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450.rss">Rebol Foundation</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rebol Foundation</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[gchiu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Ultimately we want to adapt them to R3 which is currently named Ren-c. But first step is to preserve them.</p>
<p><a class="mention" href="/u/rgchris">@rgchris</a> and I have  already captured the wiki on <a href="http://Rebol.org" rel="nofollow noopener">Rebol.org</a> and the script library.</p>
<p>We can't grab any documentation from <a href="http://rebol.com" rel="nofollow noopener">rebol.com</a> as Carl says it's copyright of RT or himself but the wayback macine has those anyway.</p>
<p>Carl has offered the <a href="http://rebol.org" rel="nofollow noopener">rebol.org</a> domain to the community i.e. anyone organized enough to take it.  I guess that could be us but it would be a huge job to reorganize all that content but I think it would be helpful if we to combine the r2 and new r3/renc documentation there explaining the differences for people looking to migrate.  Red still also refers to r2 documentation.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/5">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/5</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 21:33:53 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-post-450-5</guid>
        <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450.rss">Rebol Foundation</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rebol Foundation</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[BlackATTR]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Sounds good.<br>
Just to be clear: We're not looking to preserve the old Rebol documentation/reference materials, right? Instead we want to collect these materials so that they can be appropriately revised for Ren-C.<br>
Let's enumerate the list of actions/goals then. What needs to be done? (And, if you prefer, we can put together a To Do list in Trello for the few of us to split up the work.)</p>
          <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/4">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/4</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 17:51:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-post-450-4</guid>
        <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450.rss">Rebol Foundation</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rebol Foundation</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[gchiu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>It's about all of those things.  There was a discussion on Altme Rebol4 world some years ago but like most of those discussions, nothing concrete evolved.</p>
<p>As for identifying the people who want to be involved, I think they need to find their own way here.  Most of the people in the discussions before have moved on to red I think, or have been lost to the Rebol community and I doubt that they'd be interested in Ren-c yet.  Anyway the main people involved in salvaging Rebol documentation include myself and <a class="mention" href="/u/rgchris">@rgchris</a>, and we're both here already.</p>
          <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/3">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/3</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2018 23:32:11 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-post-450-3</guid>
        <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450.rss">Rebol Foundation</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rebol Foundation</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[BlackATTR]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I'd like to be part of that discussion. I think we need to identify the people who want/need to be involved. Then we need agree on a list of actions that should be taken. And: Is this about Ren-C, or just about archiving online content and docs from RT?</p>
          <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/2">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/2</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2018 15:11:39 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-post-450-2</guid>
        <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450.rss">Rebol Foundation</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Rebol Foundation</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[gchiu]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>We've talked at length for years about a foundation or committee of engaged Rebol users to help manage the Rebol assets including <a href="http://Rebol.org" rel="nofollow noopener">Rebol.org</a>, and any other domains that RT no longer wish to maintain.  I'd like this to extend to managing or help fund the new assets such as Rebol.info and Forum.rebol.info.</p>
<p>Yes, we'll need a charter and members, so if anyone has experience in these matters, let's discuss this one last time and actually get something done!</p>
          <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450/1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2018 01:36:26 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-post-450-1</guid>
        <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebol-foundation/450.rss">Rebol Foundation</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
